Register to the Holy Trinity Orthodox Seminary Manuscript Collection
Hoover Institution Archives
Holy Trinity Orthodox Seminary Manuscript Collection
1914-1963
2008C39
Holy Trinity Orthodox Seminary
11 microfilm reels (1.65 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Memoirs and other writings by Russian military officers and other émigrés, relating to imperial Russian military history, Russian participation in World War I, the Russian Revolution and Civil War, and Russian émigré affairs. Collected by Holy Trinity Orthodox Seminary, Jordanville, New York.
Administrative Information
Access
The collection is open for research
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by Hoover Institution Archives in 2008
Alternative Forms of Material Available
Full collection is available on Microfilm
Location of Originals
In part, Holy Trinity Orthodox Seminary, Jordanville, New York
Scope and Content of Collection
This collection contains individual holographs and typescripts (with occasional associated correspondence) donated to Holy Trinity Orthodox Seminary. The majority of these materials are in Russian, and include previously unpublished memoirs, historical essays and poetry. Among the authors are veterans of the White Army, whose memoirs focus, among other topics, on Imperial Russia, the revolution of 1917, the Russian Civil War, and émigré existence.
Among the manuscripts relating to the Russian Army in the First World War are V. Granberg, "27-aia pekhotnaia diviziia v boiu pod Stallupenenom i v srazhenii pod Gumbinenom," and Georgii Ottonovich Raukh, "2-aia gvardeiskaia kavaleriiskaia diviziia v Vostochnoi Prussii 23 iiunia – 7 sentiabria 1914 goda." The third volume of the memoirs of Prince Nikolai Zhevakhov, former assistant ober-prokuror of the Holy Synod, concerning his life and activities in emigration, are a continuation of two previously published volumes of memoirs covering the period 1915-1917. This third volume was never published.
Detailed processing and preservation microfilming for these materials were made possible by a generous grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities and by matching funds from the Hoover Institution and the Holy Trinity Seminary. The grant also provides depositing a microfilm copy in the Hoover Institution Archives. The original materials remain in the Holy Trinity Seminary Archives as its property. A transfer table indicating corresponding box and reel numbers is appended to this register. Any views, findings, conclusions or recommendations expressed in these materials do not necessarily represent those of the National Endowment for the Humanities.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the online catalog.
Subjects
World War, 1914-1918--Russia.; Russia--History, Military.; Russia--History--Nicholas II, 1894-1917.; Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921.; Russia--Emigration and immigration.; Holy Trinity Seminary (Jordanville, N.Y.)
Container List
- Manuscripts, 1914-1963 and undated. (Box 1)
  Holograph and typescript writings arranged alphabetically by author, with unidentified and anonymous works arranged alphabetically by title, preceding others
  - Unidentified
    - "Iskhod,", undated. (Folder 1: 1-6)
      Holograph
    - "Sovietskii soiuz – ne Rossiia,", 1947. (Box-folder 2: 1)
      Typescript
    - "Sluzhilye liudi na Rusi,", undated. (Folder 2: 2-4)
    - "Vospominaniia 1888-1926,", undated. (Folder 2: 5-12)
  - Adaridi, K., "Perezhitoe,", undated. (Box-folder 3: 1)
  - Apukhtin, S. A., "Vospominaniia,", undated. (Folder 3: 2-3)
  - Borel', Vera Mikhailovna
    - Correspondence related to manuscript, 1985 (Folder 3: 4)
    - Sorok let v riadakh russkoi imperatorskoi armii (Gen. M.V. Alekseev), undated. (Folder 3: 5-6)
  - Epanchin, Nikolai Alekseevich, Na sluzhbie trekh imperatorov, undated. (Box-folder 4: 1-3)
    Negative copy of holograph
  - Eristov, Georgii Nikolaevich, untitled, undated. (Folder 4: 4)
    Typescript, includes photograph, title page is missing
  - Efremov, Aleksei Ivanovich, "Svietloi pamiati gosudaria imperatora Nikolaia Aleksandrovicha,", 1930-1931. (Folder 4: 5)
  - Fersen-Cronendahl, Erik, von, "Die Romanow und ihre Zeitgenossen,", undated. (Folder 4: 6-8)
    Typescript, includes handwritten notes and corrections
  - Flovskii, Vladimir Aleksandrovich, V nebesnyi Ierusalim. Zhizneopisanie sviatitelia i zatvornika, ep. Vasil'surskogo vik. Nizhegorodskogo Varnavy (Beliaeva), undated. (Folder 4: 9)
  - Granberg, V.
    - "27-aia pekhotnaia diviziia v boiu pod Stallupenenom i v srazhenii pod Gumbinenom,", undated. (Folder 4: 10)
    - "Konskii sport v imperatorskoi Rossii,", undated. (Folder 4: 11)
    - "Inwiefern Russland im Jahre 1914 zum Kriege nicht bereit war,", undated. (Folder 4: 12)
      Typescript, coauthored with O. Urbonas
    - "Istoriia 13-go dragunskogo voennogo ordena polka,", 1914. (Box-folder 5: 1)
    - "Voennoe obrazovanie v imperatorskoi Rossii,", undated. (Folder 5: 2)
  - Khariton, igumen, "Ob ideale monashestva,", undated. (Folder 5: 3)
  - Kirienko, Ivan Kas'ianovich, 1613 g. ot chesti i slavy k podlosti i pozoru fevralia 1917 g. Vospominaniia, 1963. (Folder 5: 4-5)
    Typescript, includes handwritten corrections and notes
  - Kondyrev, Nikolai Konstantinovich, Ocherki filosofii russkoi istorii, 1938-1949. (Folder 5: 6-8)
  - Korenev, Mikhail Aleksandrovich, "Ternistyi put' ko Gospodu,", undated. (Box-folder 6: 1)
    Typescript. Essay based on the memoirs of Nun Feosva (Nataliia Vasil'evna Potulova), written by her nephew. Includes related correspondence
  - Krasnousov, E. M., "2-aia batareia 1-go sibirskogo kazach'iago konno-artilleriiskago diviziona,", 1958. (Folder 6: 2)
  - Longulo, P., "58-aia stat'ia punkt 8 i bol'she polveka teror,", undated. (Folder 6: 3-5)
    Holograph. Includes letter to Arkhimandrit Vladimir (Sukhobok)
  - Longulo, P., "58-aia stat'ia punkt 8 i bol'she polveka terror" (Box-folder 7: 1-3)
  - Meshcherskii, Nikita Aleksandrovich, Vospominaniia, undated. (Folder 7: 4)
    Typescript, includes handwritten corrections and related correspondence
  - Neelov, Nikolai Leonidovich
    - "Bezstrashnyi vitiaz' imperatorskoi Rossii,", undated. (Folder 7: 5)
    - "Moi otvet polkovniku Rogozhinu,", undated. (Folder 7: 6)
  - Nikodimov, I. N., "Vospominanie o Kievo-Pecherskoi lavre,", 1960. (Folder 7: 7)
  - Nifont (?), monk, "Vospominaniia,", undated. (Box-folder 8: 1-3)
  - Pokrovskii, N. P., "Lektsii po 'Vvedeniiu v krug bogoslovskikh nauk', chitaemyia na 1-v kursie Bogoslovkago fakul'teta Instituta sv. Vladimira,", 1938. (Folder 8: 4)
  - Popov, Petr, Reverend, "Prorok", "Skazka zhizni,", 1923(?). (Folder 8: 5)
  - Raukh, Georgii Ottonovich, "2-aia gvardeiskaia kavaleriiskaia diviziia v vostochnoi Prussii 23 iiunia – 7 sentiabria 1914 goda,", 1921. (Folder 8: 6)
  - Rubakh, I. N., "Polki rossiiskie (Pekhota),", undated. (Box-folder 9: 1-3)
  - Shcheglov, Alksandr, "Pis'mo zarubezhnomu episkopu preosviashchennieishemu Nafanailu (L'vovu),", 1946. (Folder 9: 4)
  - Sementovskii, B. K., "O moem ottse,", 1965. (Folder 9: 5)
  - Smogorzhevskii, Anatolii, diakon, "Paskhaliia i vopros vozmozhnosti perekhoda Pravoslavnoi Tserkvi na grigorianskii stil',", 1954. (Folder 9: 6)
    Typescript, includes related correspondence
  - Taushev, Aleksandr (later – Archbishop Averkii Taushev), "Istoriia russkoi slovesnosti,", 1923. (Folder 9: 7)
  - Timbo, I. A., "Lektsii po Tserkovnoslavianskomu iazyku, chitannyia studentam Bogoslovskogo fakul'teta instituta sv. Vladimira v 1934/35 akad. godu,", 1935. (Folder 9: 8)
  - Zhevakhov, Nikolai Davidovich, Prince, "Na chuzhbine. Avtobiograficheskiia zamietki i vospominaniia, 1920-1921,", 1944. (Folder 9: 9)
    Typescript with handwritten corrections
  - Zosima (Anisimov), arkhimandrit, "Pamiatka pravoslavnogo khristianina,", 1944. (Box-folder 10: 1)
  - Zvegintsov, Vladimir Vladimirovich, "Russkaia armiia 1914 g.,", 1959. (Folder 10: 2)